<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons of direction for iudges and magistrates. By Mathew Stoneham, minister and preacher in the citie of Norwich</title>
            <author>Stoneham, Mathew.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103465</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839218</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839218</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13000)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1258:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons of direction for iudges and magistrates. By Mathew Stoneham, minister and preacher in the citie of Norwich</title>
                  <author>Stoneham, Mathew.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3621:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS OF DIRECTION FOR IVDGES AND MAGISTRATES.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Mathew Stoneham,</hi> Miniſter and Preacher in the Citie of Norwich.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Pet. 2. 17. </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feare God, honor the King.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. 13. 1. </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect vnto the higher powers: for there is no power but of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <p>ANCHORA SPEI</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by Richard Field. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3621:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3621:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARD COOKE Knight, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas.</head>
            <head type="sub">MATHEW STONEHAM <hi>Miniſter, wiſheth the accompliſhment of all</hi> his godly deſires.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Had not ſuffered (right Honorable) theſe worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe labours of mine to haue paſſed to the preſſe, but that the importunity of many my friends haue preſſed me vnto it. <hi>Quod exemplo fit, iure fieri puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> ſaith the famous Romane Orator. The communitie of the act, may pleade an immunitie for this mine action. As the one of them was not long ſince vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in your Honorable preſence and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;
<pb facs="tcp:3621:3"/> ſo now it preſenteth it ſelfe vnto your view and peruſall. The other, which I haue added vnto it, prouided vpon the ſame occaſion to haue bene vttered here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, preached in the ſame place, at the hearing of two honorable and graue Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges now deceaſſed, being then by other neceſſary buſineſſe intercepted, reioyceth that it hath ſo fit oportunity now at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to open it ſelfe to the view of the world. Though neither of them haue ought elſe to commend them, yet <hi>Salomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will affoord them commendations in this, that they are words vttered in due ſeaſon, Pro. 25. 11. If God ſeaſon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 11.</note> with his grace (though men do not grace them with their fauours) it is as much as they expect, or I deſire. And thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending your Lordſhip to the protection of the Lord of Lords, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips poore orator, M. STONEHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3621:3"/>
            <head>THE FIRST SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EZRA 7. 26.</bibl>
               <q>And whoſoeuer will not do the law of thy God and the kings law, let him haue iudgement without delay, whether it be vnto death, or to baniſhment, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of goods, or impriſonment.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
               <hi>Rtaſhaſhte</hi> the great king of Perſia, hauing giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue to <hi>Ezra</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his people to returne to Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as may appeare by the copie of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patents of the ſaid great King to that purpoſe, verſ. 11. of this Chapter, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11.</note> authoriſeth him alſo there (according to the wiſedome of God which was in him, to ſet Iudges and arbiters ouer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3621:4"/> all the people that is beyond the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, verſ. 25. Meaning thereby no
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 25.</note> doubt, the riuer called anciently by the Hebrewes <hi>Perath,</hi> Gen. 2. 14. by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 14.</note> the Greekes <hi>Euphrates,</hi> modernely, as it is probable, by a briefe corruption of that word <hi>Frat,</hi> the maineſt of the curre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which do deuide Perſia from Iudaea, and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> called the riuer. And in theſe words now read, is ſet downe as it were a table of direction, to informe all Iudges and Magiſtrates, in their ſeuerall ſeſſions and proceſſions, what to <hi>examine, ſentence, puniſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This table conſiſteth (as I may ſo ſay) of two leaues or columnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the former containeth in it <hi>Culpa</hi> or matter of fault: the other <hi>Poena</hi> or matter of puniſhment.</p>
            <p>The leafe or columne culpable or of fault, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderable in theſe words, <hi>Whoſoeuer will not do the law of thy God and the kings law:</hi> The leafe or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumne
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3621:4"/> penall or of puniſhment, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruable in theſe words: <hi>Let him haue iudgement without delay, whether it be vnto death, or baniſhment, or to confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of goods, or to impriſonment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former leafe there be two branches: the former is the intent, the other is the extent of it. The intent hath in it three points, whereof the firſt is the maner of it, which conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth both in vndutifulneſſe, in that they <hi>do not the law of God and the law of the king:</hi> as alſo in wilfulneſſe, in that it is ſaid, they <hi>will not do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond point is the order of it, in that it is not firſt ſaid, <hi>the law of the king and the law of God,</hi> but firſt <hi>the law of God,</hi> and then <hi>the kings law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third point is the matter of it, in two particulars; the one, <hi>will not do the law of God:</hi> the other particular, <hi>and the kings law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The extent of it is, that it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not ſome, but out-ſpreadeth it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3621:5"/> ſelfe vnto all whoſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſecond leafe or columne of this table, which is penall or of puniſhment, I will then vnfold and branch it out, when I ſhall come to the ſpeciall handling of it: leſt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt I labour to propound method, I may haply confound memorie.</p>
            <p>The former branch then of the two in the culpable leafe of this table, is the intent of it: <hi>will not obey the law of thy God, and the kings law:</hi> wherein becauſe there is, maner, order, matter, the maner is firſt to be aſſumed to our handling, and that firſt in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulneſſe, <hi>do not:</hi> ſecondly in the wilfulneſſe of it: <hi>will not do, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their vndutifulneſſe appeareth, in that they do not, &amp;c. All which did ariſe from the want of obedience, as the want of obedience chiefly ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth from the roote of pride. Pride then cauſeth diſobedience, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience maketh vndutifulneſſe, <hi>not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3621:5"/> to do.</hi> Humilitie is ſubmiſſion, ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>ſubmittit,</hi> that is, putteth a man vnder his ſuperiour, not only in place for his condition, but alſo in office for action. But pride is elation, which elation <hi>effert,</hi> that is, carieth a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft, euen aboue his ſuperiours, both in affectation of place, which is am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, as alſo in preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of office, which is tranſgreſſion, that is, a going ouer or beyond a limited bound: a doing indeede of that which ought not to be done, but a not doing of that which ought to be done, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulneſſe here meant. The way then for a man to become moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, is firſt to become <hi>humilimus,</hi> moſt humble, and the meanes for a man to become <hi>humilimus,</hi> moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is for him ſeriouſly to meditate with himſelf, that he corporally is but <hi>humilimus,</hi> that is, the puddle or the ſlime of the earth or ground: <hi>ne ergo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lipſius de Conſtantia.</note> 
               <hi>efferat ſe coenum ſupra coelum</hi> (as one
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3621:6"/> ſpeaketh) let not the earthly element labour to ſurmount the heauenly fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament: which it ſhall attempt to do, if we ſhall not onely not do the law of the King, who is the immortall Gods lieutenant in earth; but of God who is the mortall Kings ſoueraigne in heauen. It is no doubt an happie combination, whereas <hi>Pauls'</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Tit. 2. 15. that is, authoritie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 15.</note> goeth coupled with <hi>Peters</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1. Pet. 2. 13. that is, ſubmiſſion
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet</hi> 2. 13.</note> and obedience. <hi>Submit your ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all maner of ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.</hi> Where there is a doing of the <hi>law of the King,</hi> becauſe there is a ſubmiſſion to <hi>all maner ordinance of man:</hi> there is a doing of the <hi>law of God,</hi> becauſe it is to be performed for <hi>the Lords ſake.</hi> It is a worthie ſaying of a learned Hiſtorian, who witneſſeth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>French hiſt. in Henr.</hi> 3.</note> that as in the perſon of a man the life conſiſteth in the vnion of the bodie and the ſoule: ſo in a kingdome, ſtate,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3621:6"/> or common-weale, the life thereof ſtandeth in the coherence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of <hi>commaunds,</hi> which be as the ſoule, and of <hi>obedience,</hi> which is as the bodie thereof. If either then (ſaith he) the ſoule of commands ſhal tyrannize ouer the body of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, by vniuſt lawes; or the bodie of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience will not receiue the law of the ſoule in iuſt ordinances, there inſueth a death to that kingdome, ſtate, or common-weale. Though <hi>ſic volo, ſic iubeo,</hi> ſo I will, ſo I commaund, be the voice of tyrants: yet for a man to adde his <hi>volo</hi> to Gods <hi>iubeo,</hi> his will to Gods command, is the harmonie of obedience.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I do conſider in the maner of this intent, is their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, in that they will not do <hi>the law of God and the kings law.</hi> Their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulneſſe foreſpoken of, may be likened to the rolling of the ſtone to the doore of the ſepulcher, Math. 27. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 60</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3621:7"/> 60. Their wilfulneſſe, in that they will not do it, is like the ſealing of that ſtone ſo rolled, to make all ſure, Math. 27. 66. The one is <hi>non obedire,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 66</note> a <hi>nolle obedire.</hi> The one putteth too the doore againſt the <hi>law of God and the king,</hi> the other barres &amp; bolts it. The one is like the ſinne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who did not obey the voice of the Lord, in marrying two ſinnes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to make a bloudie diuorce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a maried couple, I meane <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhebah</hi> and <hi>Vriah,</hi> by committing of adulterie with the one, and murther againſt the other. 2. Sam. 11. for which <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> afterward was ſo penitent, as he brake forth into this contrite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, admoniſhed by <hi>Nathan, I haue ſinned againſt the Lord.</hi> 2. Sa. 12. 13. fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 13.</note> as ſometimes the Poets feigned the gia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Anthaeus</hi> to fall, who by euery fall in his wraſtle with <hi>Hercules</hi> gained a mans ſtrength: ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> after his fal roſe againe, neuer in like maner to fal.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3621:7"/> The other <hi>nolle obedire,</hi> to nil to obey, is like the ſinne of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, in his detaining the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Exod. 5. 2. Who in the ſwelling of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. 2.</note> his heart vttered theſe words of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould obey his voice? I know not the Lord, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil I let Iſrael go. Neither wil I, &amp;c.</hi> He is not only vndutifully, but wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſobedient: therefore was his fall as the fall of an Elephant, of whom it is anciently written, that being down, he is not able to riſe againe. In the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are onely vndutifull (haply) one ſinne vpon better aduiſement may preuent another: but in them which are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and therefore hardened like vnto iron, as it is ſaid, Prou. 27. 17. that <hi>iron</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 27. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſharpneth iron:</hi> ſo one iron linke in this iron chaine of ſinne, tolleth &amp; haleth on another, till <hi>poſſe non peccare,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh <hi>non poſſe non peccare,</hi> that is, to be able not to ſinne, cometh to, not to be able but to ſinne. As the voice of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3621:8"/> tyrants ſtandeth for a law, ſo the will of traitors ſtandeth againſt the law. <hi>They will not do the law of God and the kings law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be aſſumed to our handling in the intent, is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it. In that it is not firſt ſaid, <hi>the law of the king,</hi> and then <hi>Gods law:</hi> but in that it is ſaid firſt, <hi>the law of God,</hi> and then <hi>the kings law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt neceſſarie it is, that the law of God ſhould be ſet in order before the kings law. Firſt becauſe God is greater then the king. This may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, not onely in that <hi>Dauid</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being a king, calleth God his king: <hi>My king and my God,</hi> Pſal. 5. 2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 2.</note> In that alſo <hi>he bindeth kings in chaines and nobles in linkes of iron,</hi> Pſal. 149. 8. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. 8.</note> In that (a token of homage) <hi>kings bring preſents and gifts vnto him,</hi> and thoſe not only of the <hi>Iles,</hi> but of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiſh</hi> which is <hi>Cilicia,</hi> and of <hi>Shebah</hi> and <hi>Saba,</hi> which is the rich <hi>Arabia,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3621:8"/> Pſal. 72. 10. and therfore all kings ſhall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 11.</note> worſhip him. Pſal. 72. 11. becauſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole earth conſiſteth of Iles and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent or firme land, the kings both of the Iles, and alſo of <hi>Cilicia</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> which be firme land, ſhall and do acknowledge ſubiection vnto him, in that when it pleaſeth him to put on his glorious apparell, euen in the skirts of that glorious garment his name is written, <hi>A king of kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi> Apo. 19. 16. But alſo the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19. 16</note> of God aboue the king may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, in that the great Monarkes of the earth, when they by the wings of their ambition haue bene ſo borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft, that of Kings they haue become Monarks: yet being Monarks, the leue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame ambition hath ſo ſwolne them &amp; in them, as of Monarkes (ſtill aſpiring to the higher) they would be Gods: as may appeare by <hi>Alexander</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quint. Cur. Pedio Mex. in Calig. &amp; Domitian.</note> the great amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Macedons, by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula</hi> &amp; <hi>Domitian</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Romans;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3621:9"/> and amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Perſians, by that proud Monarke, who cauſed an artificiall globe of glaſſe to be made, with a ſemblance of the Sunne, and Moone, <note place="margin">Du Bart. in 6. day the 1. weeke.</note> and Starres in it, which went from Eaſt to Weſt, &amp; according to the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular motion of it, was wheeled and caried about againe, and placed his throne in the top of it: where himſelf ſitting in maieſtie, would ſeeme a God and no man. But be it that theſe, in the great thoughts of their hearts would be taken for Gods, then the which they cannot climbe higher: yet God to defie them who would thus deifie themſelues, is ſaid to be a great king aboue all Gods. Pſal. 95. 3. and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. 3.</note> by conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, of ſuch Gods as theſe would be.</p>
            <p>The office of Dictator among the Romanes was aboue the place of a king, foraſmuch as when many kings and kingdomes were ſubiect to that State, the State it ſelf during the time
<pb facs="tcp:3621:9"/> of his authoritie, was ſubiect to the Dictator. Of this Dictator <hi>Plutarch</hi> writeth in the life of <hi>Fabius,</hi> that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">Plutar. in Fab.</note> it was lawfull for him almoſt to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thing, yet was it not lawfull for him to ride vpon a horſe. By how much God is greater then kings, as he is greater then theſe Dictators, who were commanders of kings, in that he rideth vpon the heauens as vpon an horſe, yea in that the holy Cherub becometh as his horſe, Pſal. 18. 16. and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 16.</note> the clouds are his chariot, &amp; the wings of the winde his gallerie whereon he walketh, Pſal. 104. 3. And therefore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 3.</note> becauſe God is greater then the king, Gods law in order is to be placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the kings law.</p>
            <p>Secondly it is neceſſarie that in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law of God ſhould be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before the kings law, becauſe it is wiſer then the kings law. When as the chiefeſt wiſedome conſiſteth in two points, in the knowledge of God and
<pb facs="tcp:3621:10"/> of our ſelues. The law of God like that ancient <hi>Ianus</hi> (whom <hi>Macrobuis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Macrob. in Saturnal.</note> teſtifieth to be double faced, for his wiſdome in remembring things paſt, &amp; foreſeeing things to come) in moſt plentifull maner reſpecteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both. Firſt touching the knowledge of God this law of God enformeth vs in it, not onely as God is the protector and redeemer of mankind, but alſo as he is the higheſt cauſe, and alone creator both of man and euery creature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, as writeth <hi>Thomas Aquinas: Cum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aquin.</note> 
               <hi>ſacra doctrina de Deo determinet, vt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsima cauſa, inter omnes ſapientias hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manas, non ſolùm in genere, ſed ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer eſt maxima ſapientia:</hi> When the holy doctrin doth determine of God as of the higheſt cauſe, among all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſdoms, it is not only in kind, but ſimply the greateſt wiſedome. Touching the knowledge of our ſelues, that I may paſſe by the maner, matter, and end of our creation, what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3621:10"/> other writing I beſeech you, doth ſo informe the vnderſtanding concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mans fowerfold eſtate: of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, of the law, of grace, and of glory, as this law of god doth? Search, reade, aduiſe, iudge, whether (in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon hereof) the wits and writs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the ſageſt ſort of men meerely naturall, haue not bene in this point as one ſpeaketh, but as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Ariſtot. in Metaphyſ.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: like the eye of a night-bird dazeled againſt the rayes of the Sunne. <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus</note> chargeth ſecular wiſe men with theft, becauſe whatſoeuer truth of God is to be found among them, they haue robbed from the Scriptures, as <hi>Plato</hi> the chiefe of them did from <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was therefore called <hi>Moſes Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> the <hi>Athenian Moſes:</hi> of which mind alſo is <hi>Iuſtinus Martyr,</hi> whom <note place="margin">Jusii. Mart. Apolog.</note> for this purpoſe learned <hi>Iunius</hi> citeth, writing on the ſinne of <hi>Adam:</hi> when (as a learned man writeth) there is a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3621:11"/> twofold law vnwritten, which is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Iunius de peccat. Ada. Antoni. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt. Min. de offic. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae praeſt. Orat. 2.</note> of nature or of cuſtome; or writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, which proceedeth either from God, or from man, or from both: the written law of meerely man may be changed, as of him whoſe defectiue wiſedome may be perfected; but the written law of God ſimply, or of man inſpired and directed by God ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatly, muſt not be changed, becauſe his law is like himſelfe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a perfect gift, and the nature of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is to admit nothing to be added to it, to permit nothing to be taken from it. A law which hath like God himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no change, Iam. 1. 17. or as <hi>S. Hieron. aduerſus Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinianum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 17.</note> interpreteth it, <hi>nullam diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiam,</hi> no difference. And therefore <note place="margin">Hier. aduer. Iouinian.</note> becauſe it is the wiſer law, is Gods law in order to be placed before the kings law. Thirdly it is neceſſarie that in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law of God ſhould be ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the kings law, becauſe it reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3621:11"/> a better obiect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth the law of the king. The law of the king wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth about the conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of bodies: the law of God laboureth about the ſaluation of ſoules: by how much the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule out-matcheth the bodie, by ſo much the law of God out-valueth the kings law. To let paſſe other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whereby it may appeare vnto vs that the ſoule is of more price the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodie (wherein I might be plentifull) this for this time ſhall ſuffice. The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſeparated from the ſocietie of the ſoule, becometh firſt a carkaſſe, then a carrion, declining from good to ill, from ill to worſe; from a bodie to a carkaſſe, from a carkaſſe to a carrion: but the ſoule (on the contrarie ſide) diſioyned from the fellowſhip of the bodie, aſpireth from ill to good, from good to better, from bondage to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, from libertie to bliſſe; from bondage in the bodie, to libertie from the bodie, to bliſſe in and with God.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3621:12"/> And when (in repreſentation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the great world) man is ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a litle world: man this litle world co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth of two parts, ſoule and bodie, euen as the great world of heauen (wherunto the ſoule may bee likened) and of the earth (whereunto the bodie may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.) This ſoule to this end <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Bernard.</note> reſembleth to heauen, wherein righteouſneſſe is as the Sunne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie as the Moone, which is long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and during, Pſal. 72. 7. faith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 7.</note> hope, charitie, and other Chriſtian vertues, as the ſtarres. As heauen then is more noble then the earth: ſo is the ſoule of man, which is like vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, more precious then the bodie of man, which being of the earth is earthie, 1. Cor. 15. 47. And therefore <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 154. 7.</note> becauſe it reſpecteth the better obiect is the law of God in order to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced before the kings law. Fourthly and laſtly, neceſſarie it is that in order
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3621:12"/> the law of God ſhould be ſet before the kings law; becauſe as there is no neede of a rudder where there is no ſhip: ſo there needeth no law where there is no common-weale; but there can be no common-weale where the law of God is not: for as much as where pietie is wanting toward God, there cannot be performed any dutie to man. Let Theologie die, and no policie can liue. Euery kingdome (in ſuch a caſe) will become a thraldome, euery common-wealth a Chaos, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Monarchie an Anarchy. Man muſt firſt be perſwaded that there is a God, before man wil euer reuerence the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of Gods, Pſal. 82. 1. This was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 1.</note> well known vnto thoſe ancient Sages the firſt inuentors of religion to their people (although not in verity as we haue it, but in policie, as they could haue it:) who as <hi>Pol. Virgil</hi> witneſſeth, <note place="margin">Pol. Virg. de Inuent. reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> euen in the firſt ſpring of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and ſtates, leſt they ſhould as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3621:13"/> ſoone be diſſolued as they were eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, ſupplanted as they were plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, did rather inuent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would want a religion. Thus among the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians did <hi>Hermes,</hi> among the old Latines <hi>Eanus,</hi> who alſo (as <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lactantius.</note> writeth) was called <hi>Ianus,</hi> among the Romans <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> among the Greekes <hi>Orpheus,</hi> among the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes <hi>Meliſſus.</hi> Whereas (on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide) the law of God may be, and ſtand, without a common-weale, as that which is naturally implanted in the heart of man; as might vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly appeare in thoſe Barbarians which were anciently ſtragling in the world before they had a <hi>Theſeus</hi> to congregate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into cities and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: as that which alſo at this day is proued among the rude &amp; naked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians in the Weſterne parts of the <note place="margin">Ioſep. Acost. hiſt. natural and morall, of the Eaſt and VVeſt Indians.</note> world, who by the light of nature ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge (as <hi>Ioſeph Acoſta</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard witneſſeth) a ſupreme Lord, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3621:13"/> of all things, whom they of Peru call <hi>Vuachoca,</hi> and giue vnto him the names of Excellent, Creator of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth, Admirable. And therefore becauſe no commonwealth can ſtand without the law of Cod, and the law of God can ſtand without the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale, is the law of God to be placed before the kings law.</p>
            <p>This doctrine affoordeth vnto vs the application of a two-fold inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whereof the one is, the ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Church, the other is the maintaining of the Church-men.</p>
            <p>Firſt the Church is to be ſuſtained, the arches &amp; pillars whereof are with all care and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be ſhoared and ſupported, leſt the fall thereof bring with it a co-ruine and inſeparable downefall of the common-wealth. A thing which not I but the truth it ſelf, and that with the voyce of her ſiſter wiſedome, crieth in the higheſt places <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 9 3.</note> of the citie, Prou. 9. 3. that it is to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3621:14"/> done, if not for Gods, yet for the worlds ſake; if not for the ſoules, yet for the bodies ſake; if not for the Churches, yet for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-weales ſake; if not for pietie, yet for policie ſake: becauſe neither the world, nor the bodie, nor the common-weale, nor policie, can ſtand without God, the Church, religion and pietie.</p>
            <p>The ſecond inſtruction from hence to be apprehended &amp; applied, is, that Church-men are to be maintained, both in their abilitie for their purſe, and in dignitie towards their perſons. For albeit pietie through the impietie of theſe times, may ſeeme (lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſince) to haue bene baniſhed, and with that old <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> to haue bene enforced to leaue the earth and to flie to heauen, there to make complaint vnto God of her hard vſage among men: yet Policie ſtill ſtandeth, and pleadeth ſtill for vs. This may abundantly be proued by the guiſe of the ancient
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3621:14"/> barbarous and Ethnicke people (as <note place="margin">Ioh. Bohem. de moribus om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> gent.</note> 
               <hi>Iohannes Bohemus</hi> writeth <hi>de moribus omnium gentium)</hi> both among the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Aegyptians, Aethiopians and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians. Concerning the Aegyptians, the ſame author witneſſeth, that none
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Affrica, cap.</hi> 4.</note> but they which were Prieſts ſonnes, aboue the age of twentie yeares, and well learned, might attend on their Kings: which he ſeemed to haue bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed out of <hi>Diodorus Siculus, lib.</hi> 2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diodo Sicu, lib.</hi> 2.</note> That alſo when the reuenewes of the land of Aegypt were deuided into 3. parts, the firſt part was due vnto and deuided among their Prieſts, as they which were of the greateſt eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, partly for the adminiſtration of the ſeruice of their gods, partly for their learning and wiſdome, partly alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were as oracles to the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie for wiſedome and counſel. The ſecond part went to the King, to theſe ends: that it might maintaine his own royall eſtate, that ſecondly it might
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3621:15"/> ſuſtaine the charges of his warres, and that thirdly it might be a fountaine of his bounties towards men of the beſt deſerts. The third part was ſhared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the penſioners &amp; men of war.</p>
            <p>Touching the Aethiopians of old <note place="margin">Iob. Bohem. Ibid.</note> time, the ſame Author in the ſame place reporteth, that they were wont to chuſe their Kings of their Prieſts, and of ſuch amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them as they knew to be more religious then the reſidue. A cuſtome alſo (if not at this day) yet not long ſince vſed in Iſeland, as <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldus Cambrenſis</hi> writeth in his To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pographie of Ireland. <hi>In Hiſlandia</hi>
               <note place="margin">Girald. Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. Topograp. Hiberniae.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>vtuntur eodem Rege, quo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdote, eodem Principe quo Pontifice. Penes enim Epiſcopum tam regni quàm ſacer dotij iura conſiſtunt:</hi> that is, in Iſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land they vſe the ſame man for a King and Prince whom they vſe for a Prieſt and Biſhop. For the rights aſwell of the kingdome as of the Prieſthood, are in the power of the Biſhop. A
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3621:15"/> guiſe alſo among the famous old Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, who when they could beare anie thing better then the name of a King in their common-weale, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained they ſtill (an honour no doubt vnto that order) <hi>nomen Regis ſacrificu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li:</hi> the name of the ſacrificing King, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their Prieſts. The Patriarkes were kings and prieſts in their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> without doubt by the direction of the ſpirit of God, ioyneth royall prieſthood together, 1. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet. 2. 9. Hierome.</hi>
               </note> Pet. 2. 9. whereupon <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ecce cum Regali dignitate Sacerdotium copulauit:</hi> Behold he hath coupled the Prieſthood with the Royall dignitie: and his Maieſtie in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> affirmeth, that <hi>Rex non eſt merè laicus,</hi> that a king is not meerely laical: which ſhew that the kingdome and prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood are not incompatible. In Arabia likewiſe the old <hi>Panchaiani</hi> (as the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob. Bohem. in Aſia. ca.</hi> 2</note> ſame Author auoucheth in the ſame booke) deliuered their cuſtomes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3621:16"/> and all their profites into the hands of their prieſts, who might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their diſcretion, as they found it neceſſary &amp; expedient, iuſtly diſtribute them to euerie man as he had need. What ſhould I ſpeake of the honor that the old Saracens did beare vnto the Caliph of Babylon? from whom (an honour greater vnto their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rich. Knols gener. hist. of Turkes, pag.</hi> 57.</note> Prieſthood, then we can either expect or dare warrant in ours:) from whom (I ſay) the great Sultans of the Turkes and Saracens, before the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> houſe was eſtabliſhed, tooke their authoritie, as from their ſuperiours, the true ſucceſſors of their great prophet <hi>Mahomet:</hi> or of the high account and eſteeme that the <hi>Grand-Segnior</hi> at this day of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> line maketh of his <hi>Muphti</hi> or <hi>Mophti,</hi> that is, his Metropoliticall Prieſt or chiefe Biſhop, without whoſe aduice &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell he vndertaketh no matter of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. If alſo anie inferiour prieſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3621:16"/> of the Mahumetane law at this day, ſhal haue any outrage done vnto him, in being violently ſtriken, if he be a <note place="margin">In Turkiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Turke which ſo doth, he loſeth his right hand; but if he be a Iewe or a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is burnt aliue for it? What ſhould I alſo remembrance you, of what eſteeme and regard euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie barbarous Chriſtians haue made their prieſts and prieſthood, euen to theſe times, among the Ruſſes and Affricans? among whom the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Ruſſia ſaith of his Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, that he is Gods ſpirituall officer, and himſelfe but his temporal officer: therefore leadeth the Emperour the
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſcouery of Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Ant. Ienkinſon. pag.</hi> 34 3.</note> Metropolitanes horſe on Palme-ſun day, and on twelfe day the Emperour ſtandeth by on foote, whiles (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome) the Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane ſitting on horſebacke, bleſſeth the waters of the riuer Moſco. The great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mander of Affrica alſo, whoſe power is commonly a thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3621:17"/> men and fiue hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred Elephants, is called by the name, not of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, Emperour, or King, but is ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (as he thinketh) by a phraſe of far greater glorie, that is, <hi>Presbyter</hi> a Prieſt. In whoſe largely exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire there be foure orders: whereof the Prieſthood is of the firſt and moſt eminent: the ſecond of Sages, called alſo <hi>Balſamates</hi> or <hi>Torquates:</hi> the third of the Nobilitie: the fourth of the Periſioners and men at armes. All which (and more then which, that might be alledged) ſhould moue vs with all loue and induſtrie to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine church-men, if not for pietie ſake, yet for policie ſake. That ſeeing men of that coat and calling can haue litle helpe (as theſe times be) by piety, which is as the bodie of Chriſt, yet with the woman we may be cured and medicined, Math. 9. 20. at leaſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 9. 20.</note> wiſe by policie, which is as the he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of Chriſts garment.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3621:17"/>
            <p>The third thing to be aſſumed to our handling in the intent, is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, in two particulars. Firſt, <hi>will not do the law of thy God:</hi> ſecondly nor <hi>the kings law. Will not do the law of thy God, &amp;c.</hi> There is a threefold tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor of the law of God, which if they ſhall not onely be vndutifull but wilfull, deſerue a more ſharper edge of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be inflicted on them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is he that tranſgreſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the doctrine of the law, as it is the ſubiect of faith. Theſe be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, who defend ſome <hi>dogma</hi> or ſelf hatched opinion (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>contra verbum cum pertinacia,</hi> againſt the word with ſtubburnneſſe, induced by one, two, or all theſe three allurements: vaineglorie, gaine, and flatterie of great men that way incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For vaineglorie, <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> ſaith: <hi>Initia haereticorum, vt ſibi placea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> they
<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> are the beginnings of Heretikes, to pleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: according to which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3621:18"/> 
               <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writeth in Zach. 13. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron. in Zach.</hi> 13.</note> they conceiue they turne it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an idoll. The couetous man wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippeth his Mammon, and the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike <hi>dogma quod finxit,</hi> the opinion which he hath coined. For gaine, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment or flatterie, <hi>Theodoret</hi> tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<note place="margin">Theodoret.</note> 
               <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus</hi> for an inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, who being ledde with hope of great gaine and preferment, which he expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from <hi>Zenobia</hi> Queene of Arabia, fell into that hereſie which afterward became his ouerthrow. The ſecond tranſgreſſor againſt the law of God, is he which tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſeth againſt the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall precepts of the law, as it is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of life and maners. This is chiefly done by theſe principall meanes.</p>
            <p>Firſt by blaſphemie, which word is deriued <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of violating or hurting the great, holy, and reuerend name of God, by vaine oathes, falſe oathes, imprecations, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſmes, &amp;c. A thing was it, ſo puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3621:18"/> by <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Emperour, as he <note place="margin">Iuſtinian.</note> that did prophanely ſweare (oh a thing very vſual in theſe times) by any member of God, or by his haire, or did anie way blaſpheme God, he died for it.</p>
            <p>Secondly it is done by murther, which is an vnlawfull taking away of the life of man by man, whether it be by an immediate act by himſelfe, or <hi>auxilio</hi> and <hi>conſilio,</hi> by ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate aide or counſell from another. Murther is a ſin ſo abhorred of God, as that it may not go away vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, he <hi>maketh inquiſition</hi> for it, Pſal. 9. 12. Yea vnleſſe a man <hi>hate bloud,</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 12.</note> as God doth <hi>hate bloud, bloud ſhal pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue him.</hi> And to ſhew the certaintie of it, it is doubled againe, euen <hi>bloud ſhall purſue him.</hi> Ezech. 35. 6. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 35. 6</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly it is done by theft, which God hath not onely forbidden as a breach of a branch of the Decalogue, Exod. 20. 15. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale:</hi> but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 15</note>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3621:19"/> alſo by making thoſe fowles &amp; beaſts which are giuen to prey and rauine, an <hi>abhomination.</hi> Leuit. 11. This ſinne <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 11.</note> in the time of <hi>Edmund Ironſide</hi> could ſcantly be found in this land, but in theſe dayes this kingdome ſwarmeth with manie an <hi>Autolicus,</hi> of whom <hi>Ouid</hi> reporteth, that he was <hi>furtum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genioſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> 
               <hi>ad omne,</hi> his crafts-maiſter to proue a maiſter thiefe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly it is done by adulterie. This God ſo deteſteth, as he would not haue it once named amongſt vs, as it becometh Saints, Epheſ. 5. 3. It is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 3.</note> the verie ſource &amp; ſpawne, fountaine and foment of fearfull murtherings and poiſonings, euen betwixt them who being coupled in one yoke of matrimonie, ought to be moſt neare one to another, in regard of a foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold combination, of goods, names, bodies, and minds alſo, but that this luſtfull monſter, like vnto the ſword of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, cutteth in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3621:19"/> the <hi>Gordian</hi> knot of loue: yea (as hiſtories be too ful of ſuch examples) of life alſo.</p>
            <p>Fiftly and laſtly (becauſe I cannot inſiſt vpon all) it is done by drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: which is not onely a tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it ſelfe, but a mother ſinne to all the reſidue. For when (I beſeech you) is a man more readie to blaſpheme, kill, ſteale, breake wedlocke, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it may be ſaid of him, that he is affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as that Emperour was, which for
<note place="margin">Bonoſus.</note> his ouer-much drinking was called a bottle. Manie good lawes haue bene made for the reſtraining of this ſinne, but they died as it were in their birth, becauſe they haue bene enacted but not acted, written in glaſſe not in braſſe. Cities and corporations (for the moſt part) are as ful of Alehouſes, Alehouſes as full of drunkards, and drunkards as ful of ſinne, as they were before theſe lawes were publiſhed, which were (it ſhould ſeeme) decreed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3621:20"/> rather to be put to execution, then to be put in execution.</p>
            <p>The third tranſgreſſor of the law of God, is he which tranſgreſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them both, that is, both the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall &amp; morall precepts of this law: theſe are the Atheiſts, who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no life but this, no God but their pleaſures; who ſleeping in, and being ouerwhelmed with ſenſualitie and ſecuritie, although they be men, yet haue the firſt ſparkles of nature more quenched in them, then the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephant being but a beaſt, yet of all other creatures coming neareſt vnto man, for his diſciplinable apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, acknowledging a Deitie therein, doth he worſhip the Moone, and Sunne, and ſtarres at euery change.</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the intent, is that they <hi>will not do the kings law.</hi> From hence may I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue both confutation &amp; inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Firſt from hence may I deriue a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3621:20"/> confutation of them who wold haue the Prieſt to be a <hi>medium</hi> of ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betwixt God and the King: when here by the Spirit of God immediatly after God is placed the King, as he who (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> writeth <hi>ad Scapu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. ad Scapulam.</note> is <hi>next vnto God, and obtaineth from God whatſoeuer he hath, onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior vnto God.</hi> As this anciently was, ſo ought it now to be: a ſubordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not of God, <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> but of God, <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> to ſhew that <hi>Aaron</hi> muſt be vnder <hi>Moſes</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> vnder God.</p>
            <p>Secondly from hence I may deriue inſtruction, of a twofold leſſon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the former concerneth the King, the later the ſubiect. The former leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon inſtructeth the King in an awfull reuerence towards God, that as God is placed before him, ſo he ſhould place God before him. Kings are the <hi>children of the moſt High,</hi> Pſal. 82. 6. As <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 6.</note> the child therfore yeeldeth reuerence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3621:21"/> to his father: ſo ought kings as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to God their Father. The other leſſon inſtructeth the ſubiect in a duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience, that foraſmuch as the king is placed next &amp; immediate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, ſo he obeyeth him in &amp; for God, if he ſhall not be contrarie vnto God. The authoritie of the King is then diſauthorized, when he ſhall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand that which is euil, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that which is good: for the Kings ſcepter and priuiledge chiefly lyeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in things of a meane and indifferent nature. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie then the Kings command in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters indifferent, it is to encounter his authoritie in the beſt title of it; a guiſe of ſome, who (haply) for their zeale may be commended, for their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance are to be pitied, for their ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnneſſe, in that they <hi>will not do the kings law,</hi> are to be puniſhed. Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the intent.</p>
            <p>The ſecond point in the culpable
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3621:21"/> leafe of this table, is the extent of it. <hi>Whoſoeuer will not, &amp;c.</hi> It is not then to be required of ſome, but to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for from all. <hi>Whoſoeuer:</hi> This I can but point at, not proſecute. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond leafe or columne of this table is penall, or of puniſhment. This is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed firſt more generally in 3. mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, whereof the firſt is the denuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſentence, in the <hi>hauing of iudgement:</hi> the ſecond, the expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, <hi>without delay:</hi> the third is the applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it, which is ſet down both in <hi>ſpecie,</hi> or more ſpecially, <hi>let him:</hi> as alſo <hi>in genere,</hi> or more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, <hi>whoſoeuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly this leafe or columne is propoſed more particularly in foure branches: firſt by <hi>death:</hi> ſecondly by <hi>baniſhment:</hi> thirdly by <hi>confiſcation of goods:</hi> fourthly by <hi>impriſonment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of the three me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers more generally propoſed, is the denuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a iudgement, in the <hi>hauing of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3621:22"/> iudgement.</hi> This <hi>hauing of iudgement,</hi> both authoriſeth the Iudge, and alſo diſcourageth the offendor.</p>
            <p>Firſt it authoriſeth the Iudge: for he that commandeth the Iudge that he muſt do it, authoriſeth alſo the Iudge that he may do it. Iudges are of Gods owne raiſing, Iudg. 2. 16. and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 2. 16.</note> alſo of Gods aſſiſting, as <hi>with whom the Lord is ſaid to be,</hi> Verſ. 18. Therfore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 2. 18.</note> authoritie cannot be controuerted, vnleſſe God himſelfe in ſome ſort be countermanded. For the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this iudgement, we muſt know that there is a threefold iudgement, <hi>Coeli, ſeculi, conſcientiae,</hi> ſupernall of heauen, internall of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, externall of the world. Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this place is not to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſupernall iudgement of heauen, neither yet for the internall iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of conſcience, but for the externall iudgement of the world: whereunto God incourageth the heads of Iacob,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3621:22"/> and the Princes of the houſe of Iſrael, Micah. 3. 1. <hi>Heare ô ye heads of Iacob,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micab.</hi> 3. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and ye Princes of the houſe of Iſrael, ſhould not you know iudgement?</hi> which <hi>iudgement, S. Hierome</hi> interpreteth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">S. Hierome.</note> for right reaſon, or adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice, according to that Pſal. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 1.</note> 72. 1. <hi>Giue thy iudgement vnto the king ô Lord, and thy righteouſneſſe vnto the kings ſonne. Iudgement to the king,</hi> that is, adminiſtration of iuſtice. Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and iuſtice in the Scriptures ſeeme to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, words of one ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification. Yet <hi>Dauid</hi> Pſal. 94. 15. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. 15.</note> them, where he ſaith, that <hi>Iudgement ſhall returne to iuſtice.</hi> In which place, iudgement (as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable) is taken for the execution of the ſword, and iuſtice for equall deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of matters in controuerſie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this hauing of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t diſcourageth the offendor, in that though for a time he hath runne on his heedleſſe and heady race, in being
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3621:23"/> both vndutifull and wilfull againſt <hi>the law of God and the kings law:</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding God hath a time wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he that would not ſubmit himſelfe vnto the tenour of the law by doing, ſhal be enforced to yeeld himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the terror of the law, by ſuffering: for there is not onely iudgement paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but execution out againſt ſuch: <hi>Let him haue iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond of the three members more generally propoſed, is the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the ſentence, <hi>without delay. Priùs conſulto, deinde maturè facto opus eſt:</hi> a Iudge muſt firſt determine with deliberation, and then (what he hath once ripely determined) act with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition. A long ſuite hanging in the Court of a Iudge, will be no more grace vnto him, then a long ſore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hand of a Chirurgian: which may (peraduenture) increaſe his coine, but wil decreaſe his credit. The cauſe of a poore man muſt not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3621:23"/> before the barre of a Iudge, as the diſeaſed poore man lay before the poole of Betheſda, euen eight &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares, and was not cured, Ioh. 5. 5.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 5.</note> The reaſon wherof was, becauſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an Angell came and troubled the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, another ſtepped in before him, &amp; was healed. But the cauſe herein muſt be inuerted; for whereas there was firſt the troubling of the water by an Angell, and then the ſtronger ſtept in before the weaker: here it muſt be deemed, that firſt the ſtronger ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth in before the weaker, and then troubleth the water with angels. The Lion (as we know) is not onely va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant but ſwift. The throne of <hi>Salomon</hi> was garded on both ſides with Lions, 1. Reg. 10. 20. hieroglyphically (as it <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 10. 20.</note> were) to ſet foorth vnto vs, that they which ſit on thrones ſhould be as Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not only in abilitie of action, but alſo in agilitie of expedition. As God is ſaid to be againſt the ſooth-ſayers,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3621:24"/> adulterers, falſe ſwearers, oppreſſors, a ſwift witneſſe, Malach. 3. 5. ſo they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. 5.</note> who ſit vpon Gods ſeats, againſt ſuch malefactors ought to become ſwift Iudges. A thing was this ſo carefully prouided for in the Iewiſh common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as their iudgement ſeats were in the gates of their Cities, Ruth. 4. 2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth.</hi> 4. 2.</note> A meanes of the more quicke diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall, ſo that there might be iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without delay.</p>
            <p>The third of the three members more generally propoſed, is the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the ſentence, which is to be handled firſt in <hi>ſpecie,</hi> or more ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>let him:</hi> that is, him who hath bin thus vndutifully and wilfully diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient againſt <hi>the law of God, and the kings law.</hi> Let him euen in his owne perſon, that as he in his owne perſon hath done what he ſhould not: ſo him ſelfe in his owne perſon may ſuffer what he would not. The Iudge muſt take heed of <hi>Herods</hi> miſcariage, who
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3621:24"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiuing a diſpleaſure againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> vniuſtly bathed his ſword in the bloud of all the innocent babes of the male ſexe, <hi>in Bethleem and the coaſts therof, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two yeares downeward,</hi> Math. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 2. 16.</note> 2. 16. Secondly this application is to be handled <hi>in genere,</hi> or more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, as this <hi>him</hi> hath a reference to the forenamed <hi>whoſoeuer.</hi> The Iudge muſt be in Gods ſeate like vnto God himſelfe, who <hi>reſpecteth no mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Act. 10. 34. but ſaith of euery <hi>ſoule</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 34.</note> 
               <hi>that ſinneth, that it ſhall die the death,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek</hi> 18. 20.</note> Ezech. 18. 20. He muſt not be affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with feare, nor blinded with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, nor corrupted with Iucre, but euen as the needle of the compaſſe pointeth alwayes towards the North: ſo ought he to haue a perpetual aſpect toward Iuſtice. <hi>Iudex cordatus, lapis quadratus:</hi> a couragious Iudge is like a quadrangular ſtone, which what way ſoeuer you ſhall turne, it lieth quadrangular ſtil, or like a mountaine
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3621:25"/> firme in it ſelfe and defenſiue for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in which the people may make them caues, and ſtrong holds againſt their aduerſaries: as the Iſraelites did in the mountaines againſt the Madia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, Iudg. 6. 2. This is the meanes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 6. 2.</note> for the Iudge to be loued of good men, and to be feared of the euill; An example hereof we haue in the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch hiſtorie, in the Duke of Aniou, being
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Charl.</hi> 9.</note> afterward <hi>Henry</hi> the third of France, who notwithſtanding the mediation of many Lords and Captaines to the contrarie, put a certaine Captaine, a Turke by nation, to death for mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold robberies and ſpoiles, whereof he was conuicted: whereupon (ſaith the hiſtorie) he was well thought of by all good men, and feared by the euill. In the ſecond place of this penal leafe or columne of this table, are propoſed foure particular limmes, whereof the firſt is <hi>death,</hi> the ſecond <hi>baniſhment,</hi> the third <hi>confiſcation of goods,</hi> and the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3621:25"/> fourth <hi>impriſonment.</hi> Of theſe ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall particulars I cannot particularly ſpeake, but muſt cloſe them all in one.</p>
            <p>Three principall qualities there be, which are craued in a Iudge (ſaith his royall Maieſtie in one of his memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble orations vttered in the Parliament houſe) courage, knowledge, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, which three qualities may be eaſily deriued out of theſe foure par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt from hence may be deriued courage, becauſe (according to the qualitie of the offence) there is not onely to be impoſed <hi>impriſonment, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of goods, and baniſhment,</hi> that is, loſſe of libertie, goods and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: but death alſo, which importeth the loſſe of life it ſelfe. Although the Iudge is to prouide what in him lieth that it may not be ſayd of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate by ouer-much ſeueritie, as it was ſometime ſaid of the Tribunall ſeate of <hi>Lucius Caſsius</hi> a Romane Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <note place="margin">Valer. Max.</note>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:3621:26"/> that it is <hi>ſcopulus reorum,</hi> that is, the Rocke of defendants and guilty ones: yet is he to know &amp; acknowledge on the other ſide, that God hath giuen him <hi>a ſword not for nought or in vaine, but to take vengeance on him that doth euill,</hi> Rom. 13. 4. <hi>Qui ſemel malus, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4.</note> 
               <hi>praeſumitur eſſe malus:</hi> he which is once euill, is alwayes preſumed to be euill. As this is ſuppoſed by law, ſo is it certainly true, vnleſſe it be tranſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by grace. The impunitie of ſinne is an inuitement to further ſinning. A worthie example hereof we haue in that late French Hiſtorian <hi>Iohn de Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. de Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> in the raigne of <hi>Charles the faire,</hi> the foure and fortieth king of France: In whoſe time a certaine Gaſcoigne vnder color of being nephew to Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. then reſident in Auinion, had his pardon for eighteene crimes by him committed, whereof the leaſt deſerued death: yet thereby could he not be reduced from his wickedneſſe,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3621:26"/> but more and more encouraged and incited to harden himſelfe therein: till in the end waxing worſe and worſe, by the counſell and iudgement of the ſaid <hi>Charles</hi> the 4. he was put to death. But in the <hi>interim</hi> that ſaying which <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> to another purpoſe vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> may herein be applied: <hi>Dum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebatur lupo, mactabatur grex:</hi> while the wolfe was ſpared, the flocke was ſpoiled: and better it had bene that one had more timely bin ended, that ſo many might not haue bene offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>The ſecond principall qualitie cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in a Iudge, is knowledge, which may alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence be deriued. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this knowledge courage is ſtrong indeed, but blind and cannot ſee, and <hi>Andabatarum more,</hi> after the maner of them who fight blindfolded, hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth as well friends as foes, the guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as the guiltie: or if it ſhall wound onely the guiltie, it may either be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3621:27"/> or defectiue, either giuing <hi>death,</hi> where <hi>baniſhment, confiſcation of goods,</hi> or <hi>impriſonment</hi> might haue ſufficed; or impoſing only <hi>baniſhment, confiſcation of goods,</hi> &amp; <hi>impriſonment,</hi> where <hi>death</hi> ſhould haue bene infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. None might come into the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <note place="margin">Picus Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randul.</note> of the Rabbins among the Iewes, vntill they could ſpeake ſeuen langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: ſo is it to be wiſhed that none might be made a Iudge, vntill he were wiſe according to the myſterie of the number of ſeuen, which is a number of perfection.</p>
            <p>The third principall qualitie craued in a Iudge, is ſinceritie or equitie, which alſo may from hence be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: without which wiſdome is lame, and though it ſeeth what ought to be done, yet neither wil nor can do what it ſeeth. This ſinceritie or equitie gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth <hi>ſuum cuique:</hi> the owne to euerie man: like that logicall rule, which is called <hi>lex iuſtitiae,</hi> the law of iuſtice.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3621:27"/> This ſorteth and fitteth euery ſcourge and puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t according to the fault and errour of the offendent or delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent: <hi>death</hi> to whom <hi>death</hi> belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, <hi>baniſhment</hi> to whom <hi>baniſhment</hi> fitteth, <hi>confiſcation of goods</hi> to whom <hi>confiſcation of goods</hi> ſorteth, and <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment</hi> to whom <hi>impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth. <hi>Iudex,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidorus,</hi> a Iudge is
<note place="margin">Iſidor.</note> ſo called, <hi>quaſi ius dicens,</hi> one that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth right, vnto whoſe tong his heart and hand ought to haue correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie, in giuing to euery man his <hi>ius</hi> or what belongeth to him.</p>
            <p>Theſe (right Honorable) are three ornaments in Iudges, which will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich and ennoble them more then the robes wherewith they are garniſhed, or the troupes wherewith they are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. A triplicitie, which if it ſhall be found in an vnitie in the perſons of Iudges and Magiſtrates, no doubt wil make them pleaſing vnto God who is trinitie in vnitie. <hi>Cornelia</hi> that chaſt &amp;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3621:28"/> famous Romane matrone (when a certaine noble woman of Campania was boaſting and glorying of her ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and ornaments) held her talke vntill the <hi>Gracchi</hi> her ſonnes came home, at whoſe returne ſhe made her this anſwer: <hi>&amp; haec ſunt orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta mea:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tiber. &amp; Cai. Gracch.</note> and theſe are my orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. If Iudges and Magiſtrates ſhall ſay of theſe three vertues, as <hi>Cornelia</hi> did of her two ſonnes, <hi>haec ſunt ornamenta mea:</hi> theſe are mine orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: oh, it wil aduance them ſo high fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thrones of their iuſtice and iudgement to the throne of Gods graces and fauours, as they ſhalbe admitted to be Iudges, to iudge for God in this world, and kings to reigne with God in the world to come. Which God graunt vnto all faithfull Iudges, and all his faithfull people, for his Sonnes ſake: to whom together with the holy Spirit, be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all honour, glorie, praiſe, power, and dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both now &amp; euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3621:28"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. CHRON. 19. 5. 6.</bibl>
               <q>And he ſet Iudges in the land in all the ſtrong Cities of Iuda, Citie by Citie, and he ſaid vnto the Iudges: Take heede what ye do, for ye execute not the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of man but of the Lord, and he will be with you in the cauſe and in the iudgement.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ehoſaphat</hi> (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) being the king and ſupreme gouernor of the land of Iuda, thinketh it a point of his dutie to ſubſtitute and depute in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour gouernours vnder him, that ſo himſelf might be the more eaſed, and his land the better gouerned: the truth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3621:29"/> whereof the drift and purport of this my text doth make plaine vnto vs. The words may be diuided into two parts, whereof the former concerne the ordination of Iudges, in the fift <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5.</note> verſe: the other the information of Iudges, in the ſixt. In the ordination <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6.</note> of Iudges there be three points of me to be handled. Firſt who were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; Iudges: ſecondly by whom; <hi>By him,</hi> that is, by <hi>Iehoſaphat.</hi> Thirdly where: firſt ſet downe more general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>in the land:</hi> ſecondly more ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in foure members. Firſt, <hi>in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Iuda.</hi> Secondly, <hi>all the Cities.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>the ſtrong Cities.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Citie by Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the information of Iudges I am to conſider: Firſt the leſſon of it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the reaſon to inforce it. The leſſon conſiſteth of three precepts, whereof the firſt is of courage: that Iudges are to do. Secondly of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: that they are to take heed. The
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3621:29"/> the third of both linked and coupled together, that they are to <hi>take heede what they do.</hi> The reaſon for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement hereof openeth it ſelfe in a twofold conſideration: whereof the former is, <hi>whoſe iudgements they do execute,</hi> ſet downe firſt negatiuely, <hi>not of man:</hi> next affirmatiuely, <hi>but of the Lord.</hi> The ſecond conſideration is, that they themſelues are to be iudged: to be collected out of theſe words, <hi>that the Lord will be with them in the cauſe and in the iudgement.</hi> If they do well, in mercy to reward them: if they do euill, in iudgement to puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Firſt then concerning the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iudges, &amp; the firſt of the three members therein contained, who were ordained, Iudges; who were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers appointed either immediatly from God, or mediatly by Kings and Princes Gods lieutenants, wiſely to heare, and indifferently to determine matters &amp; cauſes betwixt parties and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3621:30"/> parties. Wherein great care is to be had, that Iudges may firſt be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the law, according wherunto they are after to conforme themſelues and their people: for there is &amp; ought to be a mutuall reciprocation betwixt the law and the Iudge, the Iudge and the law. That as the law is a ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Iudge: ſo the Iudge may be a ſpeaking lawe. Neither ought the phraſe of the law onely to dwell in his lips, but the ſence of the law to liue in his perſon. Wherefore by a certaine learned man is he called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a liuing law or ſoule bearing iuſtice; a liuing law ſo needful, and a ſoule-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring iuſtice ſo neceſſarie in all States and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-weales, as without them they become dead and breathleſſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>cadauera</hi> then <hi>corpora,</hi> that is, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes then bodies.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the eyes of kingdoms and ſtates, which being put out, becauſe euery man will then do that which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3621:30"/> ſeemeth good in his owne eyes, Iudg. 17. 6. large limited monarchies wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud</hi> 17. 6.</note> like huge limmed <hi>Poliphemus</hi> when his eye was taken from him, in daily danger of downfall and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The neceſſitie of whom are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet downe vnto vs Zachar. 10. 4. in that they are called by the name of
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 10. 4.</note> a <hi>corner,</hi> or a <hi>naile,</hi> whoſe nature is to hold faſt and cloſe together; to ſhew that without them the veines and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of kingdomes are looſened, &amp; the knees of States do ſmite together with iarres of diſcord, and warres of homebred inſurrection, as ſometimes the ioynts and ſinewes of <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> the king were looſened, and his knees <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. 6.</note> ſmote together, at the viſion of his kingdomes diuiſion, Dan. 5. 6.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is, who ordained theſe Iudges, <hi>(he)</hi> that is, <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> the king and ſoueraigne of the land: <hi>Honos onus:</hi> honor is a cumber; and he which ſitteth on the hill of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3621:31"/> beareth a burthen on his necke as heauie as was the hill Atlas. As the Sunne therfore hauing abſolute light in it ſelfe, yet being not able alone to ſatisfie the earths contentment, len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth &amp; transfuſeth the beames therof to the orbes of the Moone and other ſtarres, which may ſupply in the Suns abſence: ſo Kings and Princes hauing abſolute authoritie in themſelues, yet being not able alone to extend the ſame to the ſatisfaction of euery ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, are enforced to depute and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordaine Viceroies, Vicegerents, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, Preſidents, Deputies, Iudges, Magiſtrates and other inferiour offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers vnder them, which may furniſh out this defect. And no maruell it is: for how is it poſſible for one man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to ſuſtaine the burthen of Gods office? Now that Kings and Princes ſtand charged with the office of God, it may appeare in that they are graced with the name of God, Pſalm. 82. 2.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 2.</note>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3621:31"/> Hence it is, that <hi>Moſes</hi> being wearie of bearing the burthen of the whole people alone, and complaining of it, Num. 11. 14. God came downe in a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 11. 14</note> cloud, and tooke of the ſpirit of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and put it on the ſeuentie ancient men that ſhould aſſiſt him, Numb. 11. 25.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 11. 25</note> Hence it is that God himſelfe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it to his people: <hi>Iudges and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſhalt thou make in the Cities which the Lord hath giuen thee throughout the tribes, and they ſhal iudge the people with righteous iudgement,</hi> Deuter. 16. 18. Hence it is that <hi>Salomon</hi> appointed twelue Princes vnder him for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning of his whole kingdome. 1. Reg. 4. 7. Hence it is that <hi>Darius</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. 7.</note> &amp; ordained an hundred and twentie gouernours vnder him, for the ruling of all the prouinces of the Monarchie: three ouer all, whereof <hi>Daniel</hi> was the chiefe, Dan. 6. 1. 2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 1. 2.</note> Hence it is that king <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt of his Princes to whom
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3621:32"/> he made his feaſt, made the ſame to his Gouernours: whereby we may obſerue he had Gouernors, Eſter. 1. 3. For this cauſe the Philoſopher calleth
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſter.</hi> 1. 3.</note> Iudges and officers thus appointed vnder Kings and Princes, in the 4. booke of his Politikes, for their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome their eyes; for their inſtruction <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtot. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. lib.</hi> 4.</note> their eares; for their protection the hands; for their ſupportation the legs of the Common wealth. And <hi>Philo Iudaeus</hi> that learned man, writing <hi>de</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Philo Judae. de creat. princip.</note> 
               <hi>creatione Principis,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Id quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae poteſtatis officium eſt:</hi> that is alſo the duty of the higheſt power or king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly authoritie, to ſubſtitute gouernors vnder him for the adminiſtration of iuſtice: for one man, <hi>quantumuis forti alacri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> corpore ſimul &amp; animo, in tanta mole &amp; multitudine negotiorum non ſufficit:</hi> though he be of neuer ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a bodie and chearfull a mind, yet in ſo great a weight &amp; multitude of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes is not ſufficient.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:3621:32"/>
            <p>The third thing is, where <hi>Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> ſet theſe Iudges, ſet downe firſt more generally, in the land: ſecondly more ſpecially in theſe foure points which in their places ſhall be handled. Firſt, <hi>in the land;</hi> without which a fruitfull land is made barren: for where the land is vngouerned, there it is vnoccupied; where it is vnoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, there it becometh a wilderneſſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 6.</note> Iere. 17. 6. with which a barren land is made fruitfull. For while as barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes chiefly proceedeth from windes, and tempeſts, and drought, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Sunne: <hi>a Prince, a Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, a Iudge, a magiſtrate</hi> is ſaid to be a hiding place from the winde, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge againſt the tempeſt, as a riuer of water in a dry land, and as a ſhadow of a great rocke againſt the parching of the Sunne, Eſay 32. 1, 2. Secondly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 32. 1. 2</note> more particularly in foure points: firſt <hi>in the cities of Iuda:</hi> old <hi>Iacob</hi> had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, Geneſ. 49. 10. that the Scepter <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 10.</note>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3621:33"/> ſhould not depart from Iuda, nor the law-giuer from betwixt his feete, till <hi>Shilo</hi> ſhould come. The truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is here furthered by <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> in that he planteth as it were a <hi>ſcepter in Iuda,</hi> and placeth a law-giuer betwixt the feet thereof, when he ſetteth Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <hi>in the cities of Iuda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cities</hi> they are prone firſt vnto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; therefore as the <hi>Greekes</hi> call a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by the name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Romanes</hi> by that word expreſſed deceit, to ſhew that <hi>cities</hi> are ſubiect to fraudulencie. Secondly, <hi>cities</hi> are prone to crueltie; therefore though <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> were the light of nations, the lady of the world and the citie of the great King, yet is ſhe called a bloudy citie, Ezech. 22. 2.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22. 2.</note> Thirdly, <hi>cities</hi> are prone to inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie: examples whereof we haue in Sodome and Gomorrha; who for that they burnt in the flames of vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall luſts amongſt themſelues, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore brought downe the flames of fire
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3621:33"/> and brimſtone from heauen, to the burning and turning of them and their cities to cinders and aſhes, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ. 19. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, <hi>Cities</hi> in a word are prone to all ſinnes and wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: wherefore <hi>Samaria</hi> which was the head citie in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is ſaid to be the wickedneſſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> Micah. 1. 5. To <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 1. 5.</note> the end then that this deceit in cities might be repreſſed, crueltie oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, incontinencie reſtinguiſhed, and all ſinnes and vices (as euill humors that craſe the health of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth) remoued, <hi>Iehoſaphat placeth Iudges in the cities of Iuda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is, <hi>all the cities, &amp;c.</hi> ſome without all, is partialitie; all as well as ſome is equitie. Equitie not partialitie ought to be the liuery and cogniſance of kings, princes and Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>Xenophon</hi> writeth in his booke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Xenoph.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: A good ruler
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3621:34"/> nothing differeth from a good father. A good father (as we know) reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth not the good of ſome of his children, and neglecteth the welfare of the reſt; but ſtandeth equally affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnto them all. Thus old <hi>Iacob</hi> Geneſ. 49. bleſſeth not ſome of his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.</note> ſonnes, and leaueth the other vnbleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but bleſſeth them all by name. A good father is affected like vnto the true mother, 1. Reg. 3. 26. who will <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 3. 26.</note> haue his whole kingdome gouerned not by peecemeale, as ſhe would haue the whole child not deuided. Vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie is a thing baſely eſteemed in theſe times, but highly regarded by <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> in thoſe dayes, who would haue his kingdome not like vnto the lap of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment rent, 1. Sam. 15.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 27.</note> 27. but like vnto the coate of Chriſt, whole without ſeame: wherefore as it is ſaid of the Spirit of the Lord, that it filleth the whole world; ſo it may be ſaid of the ſcepter of <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3621:34"/> it ruled his whole kingdome. For he <hi>ſet Iudges in all the cities of Iuda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>the ſtrong cities of Iuda:</hi> as the ſtong man is not to boaſt of his ſtrength, ſo the ſtrong citie is not to glory in her ſtrength; for might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wiſedome, and ſtrength without counſell, are like vnto huge piles of ſtuffe and ſtone heaped together without any morter or matter to combine the ſame, which are eaſily ruinated and diſſolued. One ſayth, that lawes are the life of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: execution is the life of the lawes, and the Iudge he is the life of execution. Where then there is no Iudge, there is no execution, becauſe it is as dead: where there is no execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is no law, becauſe it is as dead: where no law, there no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, becauſe it is as dead. And what ſtrength (I beſeech you) can there be in a dead thing? A certaine learned man deſcribed a law to be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3621:35"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Juni. de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit, Moſis.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, commaunding things which are to be done, and forbidding things which are not to be done: but where there is might without wiſedome, ſtrength without counſell, there things which are commanded are vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and things which are forbidden are performed, becauſe men are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with the vnbridled ſway of their owne raging appetites. And corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of men become as heards of beaſts, where not the wiſeſt, but the mightieſt beare rule: <hi>vt in grege tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus:</hi> hauing, it may be, hornes and hoofes, but no vnderſtanding. An ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Harts is but weake, yet an army of Harts (ſaith one) which hath a Lion who is ſtout and wiſe to be captain, is better then an army of Lions which are ſtrong, who haue a Hart which is white-liuerd and fooliſh to be the commaunder of them. It is ſaid, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3621:35"/> 9. 16. that wiſedom is better then <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 16.</note> ſtrength. Which may appeare vnto vs, not onely by the reaſon which <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> vſeth in the 14. and 15. verſe of that Chapter, of a little Citie which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 14. 15.</note> had few men in it, and of a great king which layd ſiege vnto it, and builded a fort againſt it; and of a poore man therein, who was wiſe, who deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it by his much wiſedome: but by a particular inducement of ſpecial ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments amongſt our ſelues, as of the fierce horſe, of the mightie Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, of the ſtrong Camell, which by the wit and wiſedome of man are tamed and made pliant to the vſe and ſeruice of man. If then the ſtrength of <hi>Sampſon</hi> lay in the haire of his head, which being taken away, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as the ordinary ſtrength of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, Iudg. 16. 19. much more <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16. 19</note> doth the ſtrength of kingdomes and ſtates lie in their Iudges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, which are not as the haire of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3621:36"/> their heads, but as the heads them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which being remoued, king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes may ſay as ſometime <hi>Dauid</hi> the king ſaid, My ſtrength is dried vp like a potſheard, Pſal. 22. 15. Be it then <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 15.</note> that it may be ſaid of our Cities, as of <hi>the Cities of Iuda,</hi> that they are ſtrong Cities: yet is it not to be ſuppoſed that they are inuironned with walles of braſſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <note place="margin">Jſocrat.</note> of rulers is as a wall of braſſe vnto cities and common-weales, as writeth the philoſophicall Greeke O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator; without which, though the ſtones of our walles be for their ſtrength as rockes, yet will they proue but rockes of wracke and confuſion to the inhabitants therein. As wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome without iuſtice is ſubtiltie, ſo ſtrength without wiſedome is cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and the people which are in ſuch a caſe, may be ſaid to eate the ſtrength of their owne skin, Iob. 18. 13. like to
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 18. 13.</note> huge <hi>Pyramides</hi> and <hi>Coloſsi,</hi> which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3621:36"/> being not well ſet together, or ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, do fall by their owne weight: ſo theſe by their owne force, as <hi>Saule</hi> by his owne ſword, 1. Sam. 31. 4. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Citie by Citie.</hi> As God made the <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 31. 4.</note> world by order, ſo will he haue it to be gouerned by order; without which it ceaſeth to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, a beautie ariſing of things ſet in order, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to be a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is a deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie growing of things hudled and confounded together: which here <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat</hi> reſpecteth in that he ſetteth <hi>Iudges in all &amp;c. City by City.</hi> Zach. 11. 7 calleth Order by the name of Beauty. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 11. 7.</note> The Greeks call beauty <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is of inticing or alluring: becauſe it doth or ought to allure all men to the gaze and embracement of it: ſo beautifull is it, and ſo fruitfull.</p>
            <p>The ſecond generall head of my text doth concerne the Information of Iudges in verſe the ſixt, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</note> firſt of a leſſon, ſecondly of a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3621:37"/> reaſon for the inforcement thereof. The leſſon ſtandeth vpon three pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, whereof the firſt concerneth <hi>courage that they are to do:</hi> what Iudges haue maturely purpoſed, that is by them effectually to be performed, not ſuffering themſelues to be aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted firſt by anger: for as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſpeaketh, we vſe not troubled water till it be ſetled, neither ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to vſe a troubled minde till it be quieted. Secondly not corrupted by gifts: for gifts blinde the eyes of the wiſe, Exod. 23. 8. Thirdly not eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 23 8.</note> by fauour; but as the ballance weyeth the gold that is precious, and the lead that is baſe, both alike: ſo to ſtand equally affected to the high and to the low, to the honorable and the baſe, the rich and the poore, one and other. Fourthly, not auerted by the ſuites and mediations of friends, but to be affected for iuſtice, as he was for truth, who ſayd, <hi>Socrates</hi> is my friend,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3621:37"/> and <hi>Plato</hi> is my friend, but truth more my friend; ſo iuſtice is moſt my friend. Fiftly, not peruerted by the wreake of priuate teen, or the reuenge of our owne priuate quarrell, but in the place of God to be like God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who (Math. 5. 45.) not ſuffereth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 45.</note> but maketh (which hath an emphaſis in it) his <hi>Sunne</hi> to ſhine as well vpon the bad as vpon the good, and his rain to fall as well vpon the vniuſt as vpon the iuſt: ſo to beare an euen hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them that loue them, &amp; them that hate them, their friends and their enemies. Sixtly and laſtly, not daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or diſmayed with any dangers or perils: for dangers and fearfull things are the true obiect of true fortitude; without which it can no more be ſaid to be true courage, then <hi>Iudas</hi> his kiſſe was true frienſhip.</p>
            <p>Oh it is a happy thing, when it may be ſaid concerning any ſtate, as Naum <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Naum</hi> 2. 3.</note> 2. 3. that they which are in ſcarlet are
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3621:38"/> valiant men: and men may witneſſe concerning their Iudges and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, as the Angell doth of <hi>Gedeon:</hi> The Lord is with thee thou valiant man, Iud. 6. 12. What is it that cauſeth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 6. 12.</note> hiſtories to report of certaine flames of <hi>Maieſtie</hi> that ſparkled in the eyes and countenances of <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius?</hi> and chiefly, as <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports <note place="margin">Sueton. in Aug. Caeſar.</note> in his life, of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar?</hi> but that they were full of courage, full of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, full of magnanimitie. Faint courage is worſe then ignorance, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance (it may be) betrayeth a cauſe for want of knowledge, but faint cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage (contrary to the priuity of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) betrayeth right for want of ſpirit. Holy anger then is well befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Iudge, well beſeeming a magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; I meane not that anger which blindeth their wiſedome, but that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which whetteth their courage. This anger it hath bene found in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in Chriſt,</hi> in holy men from time
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3621:38"/> to time; whereunto the Apoſtle exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in Gal. 4. 18: It is good alwaies <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 18.</note> to be earneſt in a good matter; the word in the originall hath an empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, to be erneſt with heate &amp; feruency: &amp; <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>Qui caret ira, caret iuſtitia,</hi> He which <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> wanteth anger, wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth iuſtice; becauſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ought to do, he leaueth off to do. The ſecond precept contained in this leſſon, is that they are to take heed: wherein I obſerue their wiſedome: none may be ſuperior in place aboue other, but hee which is ſuperiour in grace aboue other, beautified as much as may be with the ſeuen-fold grace of the ſpirit of God, wherof the ſpirit of wiſedom is ſaid to be one, Eſa. 11. 2. Where Iudges &amp; magiſtrates may be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 11. 2.</note> ſaid to be made drunk with the cup of follies, as the kings of the earth are ſaid to be drunk with the cup of the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſhameles ſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet, ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in Apo. 17. there muſt needs enſue <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17. 2.</note>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:3621:39"/> firſt reeling, ſecondly tripping, third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouerturning, both to themſelues, as alſo to the ſtate which is weilded by them; as excellently writeth <hi>Plato:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <note place="margin">Plato.</note> gouerner ouerthroweth al things, whether it be a chariot or a ſhip, or a nauie, or whatſoeuer elſe is guided or commanded by him. There be (ſaith <hi>Heſiodus)</hi> three ſorts of men in euery
<note place="margin">Heſiod.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth: the firſt are the worſt, who can neither informe themſelues, neither yet are willing to take infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from others. The ſecond of a meane ſort, ſuch as (it may be) cannot inſtruct or informe themſelues, and yet are willing to receiue inſtruction or information fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others. The third ſort be the beſt, who can both inform and inſtruct themſelues, and are able to giue information &amp; inſtruction to others: theſe be Iudges &amp; magiſtrates,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3621:39"/> which when they are wanting in any ſtate &amp; common-weale, woe be vnto that ſtate, woe be vnto that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, becauſe the Princes thereof are as children, Eccleſiaſt. 10. 16. <hi>Vbi ſtulti</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle</hi> 10. 16</note> 
               <hi>prudentibus praeſunt,</hi> as excellently wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Cleomenes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Plutarch in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; Agis.</note> and <hi>Agis:</hi> where fooles are ouer wiſe men, there it fareth with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth as with a Serpent, where the tayle laboureth to rule and draw the head after it. <hi>Plato</hi> writeth in his former <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> that the heire ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent
<note place="margin">Plato in pr. Alcib.</note> to the Perſian Monarchie, as ſoone as he had attained to fourteene yeares of age, was deliuered to foure moſt choice and principall men that could be found in all the prouinces of the <hi>Monarchie</hi> to be brought vp, and nurtured in foure of the moſt choiſe and principall vertues; whereof, the firſt was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is the moſt valiant, who ſhould traine him vp in fortitude and feates of armes. The
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3621:40"/> ſecond <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the moſt iuſt which ſhould inure him to ſpeake the truth, and to giue to euery man that was his owne. The third <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the moſt ſober, who ſhould frame his mind to that ſobrietie and temperance that he might not be conquered, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no not of one of the leaſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. The fourth and laſt he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the wiſeſt: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, who taught him wiſedome, chiefly conſiſting in the worſhip or religion of their gods, and matters concerning a King or kingly dignitie: Be wiſe therefore, ô ye kings, be learned ô ye Iudges of the earth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 10.</note> Pſal. 2. 10. that ye may not onely do by <hi>courage,</hi> but take heed by <hi>wiſedome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third precept comprized in this leſſon, is <hi>courage</hi> and <hi>wiſedome,</hi> both of them linked together in that the Iudges are to take heed what they do. The Aegyptians had an Embleme
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3621:40"/> among them, which might be a good rule of direction for Princes &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and magiſtrates, <hi>An eye with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> an eye, this argueth their wiſedome, whereby they take heede: a ſcepter, which bewrayeth their power, whereby they do: that as they are ouer men as the Eagle ouer the fowles, and the Lion ouer the beaſts; ſo they may labour for the eye of an Eagle, whereby they may ſee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to matters, firſt quickly without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, ſecondly deeply without doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, thirdly ſingly without dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling; for the heart of a Lion alſo, which is vndantable vnconquerable.</p>
            <p>The men of Iſrael teſtified concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he was worth ten thouſand of them, 2. Sam. 18. 3: ſo <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 3.</note> haue the people iuſt cauſe to ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Iudges and gouernors, You are worth ten thouſand of vs for your valiancie, worth ten thouſand of vs for your wiſedome. Wiſedome
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3621:41"/> like the wary ſpie is to go before, and Courage like a valiant army to follow after, vanquiſhing and ſubduing all things vnder it. Wiſedom informeth, courage performeth: wiſedome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth, courage effecteth: wiſedom preſcribeth, when, where, why, how things are to be done; courage ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth to do them. A Iudge or a magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate hauing wiſedome without cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, may be ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out heart; hauing courage without wiſedome, may be ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> without a head; but where they both meete together as mercie and truth did, Pſal. 85. 10. there Iudges and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85. 10</note> may be ſaid to do in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall charges, as they which bare of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice amongſt the Spartans, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, diſpoſe all things in a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull order, confound nothing by headlong raſhneſſe. Hence cometh the protecting and patronizing of the good and innocent by wiſe cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3621:41"/> the correcting and puniſhing of the euill and nocent by couragious wiſedome: inclinable indeed rather vnto mercie then ſeueritie, endeuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for that name which <hi>Minutius</hi> beſtowed vpon <hi>Fabius,</hi> as <hi>Plutarch</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Plutarch. in Fabi.</note> writeth in the life of <hi>Fabius, Quando venerabilius nomen non habeo, te mitem appello parentem:</hi> When I haue not a more honorable name to beſtow, I call thee by the name of a mild father; yet not ſo pliant to mercie as negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in iudgement: but remembring alwaies that they beare not the ſword in vaine, but that they are the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God, to take vengeance on them that do euill, Rom. 13. 4. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The parts then of the Iudges of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, are like the parts of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſong,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. 1.</note> mercie and iudgement. In the firſt place, if it may be, mercie, that they which are like God in office may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble him in image, whoſe mercy is ſaid to be ouer al his works, Pſa. 145. 9. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 9.</note>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:3621:42"/> many puniſhments are a diſgrace to the magiſtrates, as many funerals to the phyſitions, as writeth <hi>Seneca.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yet becauſe there is a ſparing cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, and a puniſhing mercy; and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh pittie ſpilleth the citie, as ſaith the prouerbe: not ſo addicted to mercie as not at all affected to iudgement, without which it is ſure that the weeds of vices would ouer-ſpread the field of the whole world, reaſon would become rage, lawes licenſe, well gouerned men as brutiſh and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage beaſts, Monarchies anarchies, kingdomes thraldoms, and the world it ſelfe a wilderneſſe. They are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as in mercie, ſo to beare the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God in iudgement, who is ſaid to haue firſt iudgement, ſecondly iudgements, thirdly armies of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Iob 10. 17: armies which are <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 10. 17.</note> for number many, for kinds ſundry, and for force mightie, beginning all things in wiſedome, following all
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3621:42"/> things ſo begun with courage, therein taking heed what they do.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing is the reaſon for the inforcement of this leſſon, which conſiſteth in a two-fold conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wherof the former concerneth whoſe iudgements they execute, ſet downe firſt negatiuely, <hi>not of man;</hi> ſecondly affirmatiuely, <hi>but of the Lord. Not of man,</hi> who is baſe, weake, miſerable in his birth, life, death: therefore may he ſeeme iuſtly to be contemned, his lawes to be wreſted, his ordinances to be peruerted, his ſtatutes to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed by him which is the publicke organ and miniſter thereof: ſo he may do it ſecretly without detection, or ſubtilly without conuiction. <hi>Not of man,</hi> who for his matter is called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Adam, red earth. Enoſh, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row or affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> which ſignifieth <hi>earth:</hi> for his miſery <hi>Enoſh,</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>ſorrow</hi> or affliction: and therefore may he and his lawes ſeeme lightly to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, baſely to be eſteemed. <hi>Not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3621:43"/> of man,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, man is full of windings and turnings: therefore ſeemeth it no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter very important, if there be a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and turning from his lawes and iudgements. <hi>Not of man,</hi> who ſetteth forth deceit with his tongue, Rom. 3. 13. therfore may he ſeeme (according <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 13.</note> to the natural ſuggeſtion of depraued reaſon) <hi>lege talionis,</hi> by law of like for like, to be worthily deceiued againe. To conclude, <hi>not of man,</hi> who hath tranſgreſſed the law of the higheſt: for there is none that doth good, no not one. It may ſeeme then no matter of great moment, when a man hath tranſgreſſed the law of God, if man violate the iudgements of man.</p>
            <p>The part affirmatiue followeth the part negatiue: <hi>But of the Lord.</hi> Of the Lord, who for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance is God from euerlaſting and world without end, Pſal. 90. 2. For his eſſence a ſpirit, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 2.</note> who will be worſhipped in ſpirit and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3621:43"/> truth, Iohn 4. 24. For his ſtate, one <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 24.</note> in whoſe preſence is fulneſſe of ioy, and at his right hand pleaſures for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore, Pſal. 16. 12. For his conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 12.</note> hath no ſhadow by turning, Iam. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iac.</hi> 1. 17.</note> 1. 17. For his ſinceritie and ſanctimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie is <hi>holy, holy, holy,</hi> not once, nor twice, but thrice <hi>holy:</hi> and that not by the opinion of men, but by the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Angels, Iſay 6. 3. Of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 6. 3.</note> Lord, who ſpanneth the heauens with his ſpan, and meaſureth the waters in his fiſt, and weyeth the mountaines in a ballance. Of the Lord, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of whom all the nations of the earth are but as a drop from a bucket. Of the Lord, who is the Lord of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whoſe paths are in the whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind and the ſtorme, and the clouds are the duſt of his feete, Naum 1. 2. 3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Naum</hi> 1. 2. 3</note> Finally of the Lord: at the preſence and in the ſight of whom the earth is burnt, the rocks cleaue, the mountains tremble, the hils melt, the deeps roare,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3621:44"/> hell it ſelfe and all infernall troupes do ſhake and ſhudder. Seeing then ye execute not the iudgements of man ſuch and ſo baſe, ſuch and ſo weake, ſuch and ſo contemptible, but of the Lord, ſuch and ſo glorious, ſuch and ſo mightie, ſuch and ſo fearfull, ſuch and ſo dreadfull, of ſuch and ſo great terror and maieſty: oh it ſtandeth you in hand to take heed what you do.</p>
            <p>The ſecond conſideration obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable in this reaſon, is, that Iudges themſelues are to ſtand at the ſeate of iudgement, to be collected out of theſe words, <hi>who will be with you in the cauſe and in the iudgement: he will be with them</hi> by the all-ſeeing eye of his vnſearchable wiſedome and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>if they do well, to reward them with mercie: if they do euill, to puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with iudgement.</hi> If then the Iudges of the earth ſhall not adminiſter iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhall not do equitie, ſhall not performe iuſtice, ſhall not beware,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3621:44"/> ſhall not take heed, ſhall haue <hi>inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentes oculos, &amp; incontinentes manus,</hi> incontinent eyes and incontinent hands: Incontinent eyes like to the two vnchaſt Iudges towards <hi>Suſanna:</hi> Incontinent hands like to <hi>Felix,</hi> who is ſaid to leaue <hi>Paul</hi> bound, becauſe he looked for money to haue looſed him, Act. 24. 27: then the Lord will <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24. 27.</note> be with them in ſuch a caſe and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the viall of his wrath, in the edge of his indignation, puniſhing them both in this world and in the world to come. In this world, as he raiſed vp <hi>Daniel,</hi> which ſignifieth the iudgement of God againſt thoſe two incontinent Iudges, who arraigned, condemned, and cauſed them to be ſtoned to death: as he no doubt alſo raiſed vp <hi>Cambyſes</hi> againſt <hi>Siſannes</hi> that corrupt Iudge, in cauſing him to be fleyed quicke, and his skinne to be hung on the iudgement ſeate for his bribe-taking. But if not in this world,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3621:45"/> moſt certainly in the world to come, when, oh fearfull ſaying, <hi>The migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall be mightily tormented,</hi> Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. 6. 6. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VViſd.</hi> 6. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But if the Iudges of the earth ſhall adminiſter iudgement, ſhall do equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſhall performe iuſtice, ſhal beware, ſhall take heed, ſhall ſeeke to be that in their ſeueral circuits, which <hi>Ariſtides</hi> was amongſt the Athenians, of whom <hi>Herodotus</hi> reporteth, that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Herodot.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, the beſt and the moſt iuſt man among the Athenians. If they ſhall be men of courage, there is fortitude; fearing God, there is wiſedome; dealing tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, there is iuſtice; hating couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, there is temperance, Exod. 18. 21. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. 21</note> which are called the foure Cardinall vertues, becauſe vpon them, as vpon their proper hinges, all other vertues do depend. Vertues fit for Iudges and magiſtrates, on whom the ſtay &amp; ſtate of common-weales and ſtates, as on
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3621:45"/> their ſeuerall hinges, are ſuſtained: then the Lord will be with them in ſuch a cauſe and iudgement, with mercie rewarding them both in this life, as alſo in the life to come: in this life with riches, wiſedom and honor; in the life to come with bliſſe, life and immortalitie. As it is comfortably written, Wiſd. 6. from ver. 17. to v. 22.
<note place="margin">VViſdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verſ. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to 22.</note> The deſire of diſcipline is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of wiſedome, and the care of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline is loue, and loue is the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the commandement; the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the commandement is the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of immortalitie; immortalitie maketh vs neare vnto God: wherfore the loue of wiſedome bringeth vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome. If then your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light be in thrones and in ſcepters (oh ye kings and Iudges of the earth) em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace wiſedome and raigne for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>Thus (right honorable) haue I ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this text vnto you, not largely
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3621:46"/> amplified, but briefly compriſed: wherein I haue ſhewed you the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of a Iudge, and the informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him. <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> ſaith, that God is
<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> one in eſſence, but diuers and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold in office and magiſtracy, whereof your honours haue a portion. Gird therefore your loynes with the girdle of fortitude, but of fortitude infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by wiſedome: let mercie and iudgement, iudgement and mercie meet in your perſons, as ſomtime the ſweete and the ſtrong, the ſtrong and the ſweet did in <hi>Sampſons</hi> riddle, Iud. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 14. 14</note> 14. 14. Go on to do that which ye do, I meane to ſhun and auoid that which is euill and vniuſt, and ſo ye may ſhun and auoid the being of God with you <hi>in the cauſe and in the iudgement</hi> puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing you. Go on to embrace that which is good and iuſt, that ſo the mercy of God may embrace you, and his louing fauor may compaſſe you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout as it were with a ſhield, Pſa. 5. 12. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 12.</note>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:3621:46"/> Let the iudgement-ſeate, whereon your honorable perſonages doe ſit, put you in mind of the ſeate of Gods iudgement: let the iudgement barre, whereat the miſerable priſoners are arraigned before you, bring to your remembrance the bar of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when the iudgement ſhall be extraordinarie, both in regard of the Iudge, who ſhall be God the Iudge of the whole world, Geneſ. 18. 25. as alſo <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 2</note> in regard of them which ſhall be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, which are the Iudges of the earth. And euer and anon think vpon that ſaying, which, the wiſer the heart is it lighteth on, the deeper impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it maketh, written Wiſdom. 6. 5. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VViſd.</hi> 6. 5</note> 
               <hi>will the Lord appeare vnto you: for a hard iudgement ſhall be for them that beare rule.</hi> Proceed therefore as to the good of this kingdome you haue begunne: proceede I ſay, and ſo long as this your life continueth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue you this proceeding, to be that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3621:47"/> vnto his Maieſtie, which his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in that his excellent ſpeech which he made in the Parliament houſe, no doubt in your honourable preſence and audience, aduiſeth you to be his eyes to ſee for him, his eares to heare for him: that as his Maieſtie deſireth to heare and ſee for the Lord; ſo ye may ſee and heare for his Maieſtie. For his Maieſtie in that his ſpeech, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly proteſteth that the thrones which you ſit on, are neither his nor yours, but the Lords. Keepe therfore iudgement, relieue the oppreſſed, iudge the fatherleſſe, defend the cauſe of the widow, <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. 17. Let that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 1. 17.</note> of <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> be as a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates <hi>memento</hi> vnto you, <hi>Quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Grego. Naz.</note> 
               <hi>leonum &amp; reliquorum animaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> motus non ſunt ijdem, ita nec magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp; populi:</hi> as the motions and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of Lions and other baſer crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are not alike, ſo neither of the magiſtrate &amp; the people. As therefore
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3621:47"/> ye manage greater matters then the people, ſo ought your cariage to be of better manners then the people: that as in places, ſo you may be aboue them in graces; that it may be ſaid of you in regard of your Iudges office, as it is ſaid of <hi>Dauid</hi> in reſpect of his kings office, that the ſpirit of God is come vpon you from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, 1. Sam. 16. 13. <hi>Plutarch</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <note place="margin">1. Sam. 16. 13. Plutarch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Demoſthen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in the life of <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> that it was a ſaying among the people, that <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> was worthy of the citie, but <hi>Demades</hi> aboue the citie. Behaue your ſelues ſo in your places, as ye may not onely be counted worthy of your places, but alſo aboue your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; that he which ſitteth aboue, may reward you both below and aboue: below in this life with riches, wiſedom and honour, waiting on your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeates, as ſometime they atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the throne of <hi>Salomon:</hi> aboue in the life to come with bliſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3621:48"/> when your ſcarlet robes ſhall be turned into long white robes, your traines of eſtate into troupes and millions of Saints and Angels: your iudging of men into iudging of Angels; and your earths authoritie into heauens glory: which God grant vnto all faithfull Iudges and all his faithfull people, and that for his Son Chriſt Ieſus ſake: to whom, together with the holy Spirit, be all honor, praiſe, power, and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion both now and for euer. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3621:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
